Clearly, we're living in a moment of crisis.
من الواضح أننا نعيش في لحظة أزمة.
Arguably the financial markets have failed us
يمكن القول أن الأسواق المالية قد أفشلتنا
and the aid system is failing us,
وأن نظام المساعدات يفشلنا.
and yet I stand firmly with the optimists
وحتى الآن أقف بحزم مع المتفائلين
who believe that there has probably never been a more exciting moment to be alive.
الذين يعتقدون أن هناك لحظة ربما لم يسبق أكثر إثارة منها لتعاش.
Because of some of technologies we've been talking about.
بسبب بعض التكنلوجيات التي كنا نتحدث عنها.
Because of the resources, the skills,
بسبب الموارد، المهارات،
and certainly the surge of talent we're seeing all around the world,
وبالتأكيد موجة من المواهب التي نراها في جميع أنحاء العالم،
with the mindset to create change.
مع عقلية لخلق التغيير.
And we've got a president who sees himself as a global citizen,
وقد أستقبلنا رئيساً يرى نفسه كمواطن عالمي،
who recognizes that no longer is there a single superpower,
ويعترف أنه لم تعد هناك قوى منفردة،
but that we've got to engage in a different way with the world.
لكننا يجب أن نشارك بطريقة مختلفة مع العالم.
And by definition, every one of you who is in this room
وبحسب التعريف، فكل شخص في هذه القاعة
must consider yourself a global soul,
ينبغي إعتبار نفسه كشخص عالمي،
a global citizen.
مواطن عالمي.
You work on the front lines. And you've seen the best and the worst
أنتم تعملون على الخطوط الأمامية. وقد رأيتم الأفضل والأسوأ
that human beings can do for one another and to one another.
الذي يمكن للبشرية أن تفعله من شخص لشخص آخر.
And no matter what country you live or work in,
ولا يهم أي دولة تعيش بها أو تعمل فيها،
you've also seen the extraordinary things that individuals are capable of,
لقد رأيتم كذلك أشياء غير إعتيادية التي يقدر الفرد على فعلها،
even in their most ordinariness.
حتى في معظم أوقاتهم الاعتيادية.
Today there is a raging debate
اليوم يدور جدل محتدم
as to how best we lift people out of poverty,
على كيفية إنتشال الناس من الفقر،
how best we release their energies.
كيفية تفجير طاقاتهم.
On the one hand, we have people that say
على جانب، لدينا الناس الذين يقولون
the aid system is so broken we need to throw it out.
أن نظام المساعدات محطم بشدة ونحتاج للتخلص منه.
And on the other we have people who say
وعلى الجانب الآخر لدينا أناس يقولون
the problem is that we need more aid.
أن المشكلة هي أننا نحتاج لمساعدات أكثر.
And what I want to talk about is something that compliments both systems.
وما أريد أن أحدثكم به هو شئ يجامل كلا النظامين.
We call it patient capital.
نحن نسميه رأس مال الصبور.
The critics point to the 500 billion dollars spent
يشير النُقاد إلى 500 مليار دولار تم صرفها
in Africa since 1970
في أفريقيا منذ عام 1970
and say, and what do we have but environmental degradation
ويقولون على ماذا حصلنا سوى التدهور البيئي
and incredible levels of poverty, rampant corruption?
ومستويات لا تصدق من الفقر، وتفشي الفساد؟
They use Mobutu as metaphor.
ويضربون مثلاً بموبوتو.
And their policy prescription is to
ووصف سياستهم هو أن
make government more accountable,
تجعل الحكومة أكثر خضوعاً للمساءلة،
focus on the capital markets,
وتركز على أسواق رأس المال،
invest, don't give anything away.
إستثمر، لا تعط أي شئ مجاناً.
On the other side, as I said, there are those who say
وعلى الجانب الآخر، كما قلت، هناك الذين يقولون
the problem is that we need more money.
أن المشكلة هي أننا بحاجة لمزيد من الأموال.
That when it comes to the rich, we'll bail out
وعندما يتعلق الأمر بالأغنياء، سنقوم بإنقاذهم
and we'll hand a lot of aid,
وسنقدم الكثير من المساعدات.
but when it comes to our poor brethren,
لكن حينما يتعلق الأمر بأخواننا الفقراء،
we want little to do with it.
نرغب في فعل القليل لهم.
They point to the successes of aid:
ويشيرون لنجاحات المساعدات:
the eradication of smallpox,
القضاء على وباء الجدري،
and the distribution of tens of millions
وتوزيع عشرات الملايين
of malaria bed nets and antiretrovirals.
من الناموسيات ومضادات الفيروسات.
Both sides are right.
كلا الطرفين على حق.
And the problem is that neither side is listening to the other.
والمشكلة هي أن لا أحد من الطرفين يستمع للآخر.
Even more problematic, they're not listening to
والأكثر إثارة للمشاكل، هي أنهم لا يستمعون
poor people themselves.
للفقراء أنفسهم.
After 25 years of working on issues of
بعد 25 من العمل في قضايا
poverty and innovation,
الفقر والإبتكار،
it's true that there are probably no more market-oriented
صحيح أنه من المحتمل أن لا يوجد أفراد أكثر توجها
individuals on the planet
نحو السوق على كوكب الأرض،
than low-income people.
من الناس ذوي الدخل المنخفض.
They must navigate markets daily,
ينبغي عليهم إستكشاف الأسواق يومياً،
making micro-decisions, dozens and dozens,
وإتخاذ قرارات جزئية، الكثير والكثير منها،
to move their way through society,
ليواصلوا مسيرتهم في المجتمع.
and yet if a single catastrophic health problem
وإذا حدثت كارثة صحية
impacts their family,
أثرّت في أسرتهم،
they could be put back into poverty, sometimes for generations.
فيمكن أن يعودوا مجدداً إلى الفقر، بعض الأحيان لأجيال.
And so we need both the market
ولذا نحن نحتاج لكلا السوق
and we need aid.
ونحتاج المساعدات.
Patient capital works between,
رأس المال الصبور يعمل بينهما،
and tries to take the best of both.
ويحاول أخذ الأفضل من الأثنين.
It's money that's invested in entrepreneurs who know their communities
إنه المال المستثمر في رجال الأعمال الذين يعرفون مجتمعاتهم
and are building solutions
ويطورون حلولاً
to healthcare, water, housing, alternative energy,
للرعاية الصحية، المياة، الإسكان، الطاقة البديلة،
thinking of low income people not as passive recipients of charity,
لا يفكرون بذوي الدخل المنخفض كمتلقين سلبيين للمساعدات،
but as individual customers, consumers, clients,
لكن كزبائن أفراد، مستهلكين، عملاء،
people who want to make decisions in their own lives.
الناس الذين يرغبون باتخاذ قرارات لحياتهم الخاصة.
Patient capital requires that we have
رأس المال الصبور يتطلب أن يتوافر لدينا
incredible tolerance for risk,
مقدرة هائلة على التسامح مع المخاطر،
a long time horizon in terms of allowing those
وأفقاً زمنياً طويلاً من ناحية السماح لإعطاء الوقت
entrepreneurs time to experiment,
لرجال الأعمال أؤلئك للتجريب،
to use the market as the best listening device that we have,
لإستخدام السوق كأفضل أداة ممكنة لنا للاستماع ،
and the expectation of below-market returns,
والتوقعات بعائدات أقل من السوق،
but outsized social impact.
لكن ذات تأثير إجتماعي كبير.
It recognizes that the market has its limitation,
إنها تعترف بأن لدى السوق حدوده.
and so patient capital also works
ويعمل رأس المال الصبور كذلك
with smart subsidy to extend the benefits of a global economy
مع الدعم الذكي لتوسيع فوائده للإقتصاد العالمي،
to include all people.
ليشمل كل الناس.
Now, entrepreneurs need patient capital
الآن يحتاج رجال الأعمال لرأس المال الصبور
for three reasons.
لثلاثة أسباب.
First, they tend to work in markets
أولاً، إنهم يميلون للعمل في أسواق
where people make one, two, three dollars a day
حيث يجني الناس دولار، دولارين، ثلاثة دولارات يومياً
and they are making all of their decisions within that income level.
ويقومون باتخاذ قراراتهم على ذلك المتسوى من الدخل.
Second, the geographies in which they work
ثانياً، الحدود الجغرافية التي يعملون فيها
have terrible infrastructure --
لديها بنية تحتية فظيعة.
no roads to speak of, sporadic electricity
لا توجد طرق للحديث عنها، الكهرباء مقطوعة،
and high levels of corruption.
ومستويات عالية من الفساد.
Third, they are often creating markets.
ثالثاً، إنهم في الغالب يصنعون الأسواق.
Even if you're bringing clean water
حتى إن جلبوا الماء النظيف
for the first time into rural villages, it is something new.
لأول مرة إلى القرى الريفية، فانها شئ جديد.
And so many low-income people
والكثير من الناس ذوي الدخل المنخفض
have seen so many failed promises broken
قد جربوا العديد من الوعود الفاشلة،
and seen so many quacks and sporadic medicines offered to them
وشهدوا العديد من الدجالين والأدوية المزيفة التي كانت تُقدم لهم،
that building trust takes a lot of time,
بحيث أن بناء الثقة يتطلب الكثير من الوقت،
takes a lot of patience.
ويتطلب الكثير من الصبر.
It also requires being connected to a lot of management assistance.
ويتطلب كذلك أن تكون متواصلاً مع الكثير من المساعدات الإدارية.
Not only to build the systems,
ليس فقط لبناء الأنظمة،
the business models that allow us
نماذج الأعمال التي تتيح لنا
to reach low income people in a sustainable way,
الوصول لذوي الدخل المنخفض بطريقة مستدامة،
but to connect those business
لكن بالتواصل مع تلك الأعمال،
to other markets, to governments, to corporations --
للأسواق الأخرى، للحكومات، للمؤسسات--
real partnerships if we want to get to scale.
شراكات حقيقية إن كنت ترغب بالتوسع.
I want to share one story
أرغب في تقاسم قصة واحدة
about an innovation called drip irrigation.
حول إبتكار يسمى الري بالتنقيط.
In 2002 I met this incredible entrepreneur
في عام 2002 إلتقيت برجل الأعمال المذهل هذا
named Amitabha Sadangi from India,
يسمى أميتابها سادانغي من الهند،
who'd been working for 20 years with some of the poorest farmers on the planet.
الذي كان يعمل ل 20 سنة مع بعض أفقر المزارعين على الأرض.
And he was expressing his frustration
وكان يعبّر عن إحباطه
that the aid market had bypassed low-income farmers altogether,
بأن سوق المساعدات قد تجاوز جميع المزارعين ذوي الدخول المنخفضة،
despite the fact that 200 million farmers
رغماً عن حقيقة أن 200 مليون مزارع
alone in India make under a dollar a day.
في الهند وحدها يجنون أقل من دولار يومياً.
They were creating subsidies
إنهم يقدمون الدعم
either for large farms,
إمّا للمزارع الكبيرة،
or they were giving inputs to the farmers
أو كانوا يعطون مساهمات للمزارعين
that they thought they should use, rather than
ظنوا أنه ينبغي عليهم إستخدامها، بدلاً عن
that the farmers wanted to use.
أن المزارع يرغب في إستخدامها.
At the same time Amitabha was
وفي نفس الوقت كان أميتابها
obsessed with this drip irrigation technology
متوجساً بتكنلوجيا الري بالتنقيط هذه
that had been invented in Israel.
التي تم إبتكارها في إسرائيل.
It was a way of bringing small amounts of water
لقد كانت طريقة لجلب كمية قليلة من الماء
directly to the stalk of the plant.
مباشرة إلى ساق النبات.
And it could transform
ويمكن أن تحوّل
swaths of desert land into fields of emerald green.
مساحات كبيرة من الأراضي الصحراوية لمساحات من الزمرد الأخضر.
But the market also had bypassed low income farmers,
لكن السوق أيضاً قام بتجاوز المزارعين ذوي الدخل المنخفض.
because these systems were both too expensive,
لأن هذه الأنظمة كانت باهظة الثمن،
and they were constructed for fields that were too large.
وأُقيمت في الحقول الشاسعة جداً.
The average small village farmer
في المتوسط يعمل المزارع القروي الصغير
works on two acres or less.
على فدانين أو أقل.
And so, Amitabha decided that he would take that innovation
ولذا قرر أميتابها بأنه سيأخذ ذلك الإبتكار
and he would redesign it from the perspective
وسيكون بإعادة تصميمه من وجهة نظر
of the poor farmers themselves,
المزارعين الفقراء أنفسهم.
because he spent so many years listening to what they needed
لأنه قضى العديد من السنوات يستمع لحوجتهم
not what he thought that they should have.
وليس ما يعتقد أن عليهم فعله.
And he used three fundamental principles.
وقد أستخدم ثلاث مبادئ أساسية.
The first one was miniaturization.
الأول كان التصغير.
The drip irrigation system
نظام الري بالتنقيط
had to be small enough that a farmer only had
ينبغي أن يكون صغيراً بما يكفي بحيث يتوجب على المزارع
to risk a quarter acre,
المجازفة بربع فدان،
even if he had two,
حتى إن كان يملك فدانين،
because it was too frightening, given all that he had at stake.
لأنها كانت مخيفة جداً، بالنظر لأنه كان على المحك.
Second, it had to be extremely affordable.
ثانياً، يجب أن يكون بسعر معقول جداً.
In other words, that risk on the quarter acre
بكلمات أخرى، تلك المجازفة بربع الفدان
needed to be repaid in a single harvest,
يجب أن تسترجع بعد حصاد محصول واحد.
or else they wouldn't take the risk.
أو لن يقوموا بالمجازفة.
And third, it had to be what Amitabha calls
وثالثاً، ينبغي أن تكون ما يسميه أميتابها
infinitely expandable.
قابل للتوسع إلى ما لا نهاية.
What I mean is with the profits from the first quarter acre,
ما أعنيه بالأرباح من ربع الفدان الأول،
the farmers could buy a second
هو أن المزارعين يستطيعوا شراء الثاني،
and a third and a fourth.
والثالث، والرابع.
As of today, IDE India, Amitabha's organization,
واليوم، IDE الهند، منظمة أميتابها
has sold over 300,000 farmers these systems
قام ببيع هذه الأنظمة لزيادة على 300 ألف مزارع
and has seen their yields and incomes
وقد شهدت زيادة في مدخولاتهم
double or triple on average,
ضعفين أو ثلاثة أضعاف في المتوسط.
but this didn't happen overnight.
لكن هذا لم يحدث بين ليلة وضحاها.
In fact, when you go back to the beginning,
في الواقع، حينما نرجع إلى البداية،
there were no private investors
لم يكن هناك مستثمرين من القطاع الخاص
who would be willing to take a risk on building a new technology
الذين يرغبون في المخاطرة لتأسيس تكنلوجيا حديثة
for a market class that made under a dollar a day,
لفئة السوق التي تجني أقل من دولار يومياً،
that were known to be some of the most risk-averse people on the planet
المعروفين بكونهم بعض أكثر الناس نفوراً من المخاطر على الارض،
and that were working in one of the riskiest sectors, agriculture.
وكان ذلك العمل في أحد أكثر القطاعات مخاطراً، الزراعة.
And so we needed grants. And he used significant grants
ولذا فقد أحتجنا منحاً. وقد أستخدم منحاً كبيرة
to research, to experiment, to fail,
للبحث، للتجريب، وللفشل،
to innovate and try again.
للإبتكار وللمحاولة مجدداً.
And when he had a prototype
وعندما توصل لنموذج مبدئي
and had a better understanding of how to market to farmers,
وتوصل لفهم أفضل حول كيفية التسويق للمزارعين،
that's when patient capital could come in.
حينها يأتي دور رأس المال الصبور.
And we helped him build a company, for profit,
وقد ساعدناه في تأسيس شركة، للربح،
that would build on IDE's knowledge,
التي ستبني على معرفة IDE،
and start looking at sales and exports,
وتبدأ في النظر للمبيعات والصادرات،
and be able to tap into other kinds of capital.
وتقدر على الإستفادة من أنواع أخرى من رأس المال.
Secondarily, we wanted to see if we could export
ثانياً، رغبنا في معرفة إن كان بإمكاننا تصدير
this drip irrigation and bring it into other countries.
هذا الري بالتنقيط وجلبه لدول أخرى.
And so we met Dr. Sono Khangharani in Pakistan.
ولذا إلتقينا بالدكتور سونو خانجاراني في باكستان.
And while, again, you needed patience
وبينما مجدداً ، تحتاج للصبر
to move a technology for the poor
لنقل التكنلوجيا إلى الفقراء
in India into Pakistan,
في الهند، وباكستان،
just to get the permits,
لمجرد الحصول على تراخيص،
over time we were able to start a company
عبر الزمن أستطعنا إقامة شركة مع
with Dr. Sono, who runs a large
الدكتور سونو الذي يدير
community development organization in the Thar Desert,
منظمة إجتماعية كبيرة للتنمية في صحراء ثار،
which is one of the remote and poorest areas of the country.
التي هي أحد المناطق النائية وأفقرها في البلاد.
And though that company has just started,
ورغماً عن أن الشركة بدأت للتو،
our assumption is that there too
كانت فرضيتنا أيضاً
we'll see the impact on millions.
أننا سنرى التأثير على الملايين.
But drip irrigation isn't the only innovation.
لكن الري بالتنقيط لم يكن الإبتكار الوحيد.
We're starting to see these happening all around the world.
بدأنا في رؤية هذا يحدث في كل أنحاء العالم.
In Arusha, Tanzania, A to Z Textile Manufacturing
في أروشا، تنزانيا A to Z لتصنيع الأقمشة
has worked in partnership with us,
قد عملت في شراكة معنا،
with UNICEF, with the Global Fund,
مع اليونيسف، مع المساعدات الدولية،
to create a factory that now employs 7,000 people, mostly women.
لإنشاء مصنع يوظف الآن 7000 شخص، معظمهم من النساء.
And they produce 20 million lifesaving bednets
وينتجون 20 مليون ناموسية
for Africans around the world.
للأفارقة حول العالم.
Lifespring Hospital
مستشفى لايف إسبرينج
is a joint venture between Acumen and the government of India
هو مشروع مشترك بين أكيومن وحكومة الهند
to bring quality, affordable maternal health care
لتقديم رعاية صحية نوعية بأسعار معقولة
to low-income women,
للنساء ذوات الدخل المنخفض.
and it's been so successful that it's currently building
وقد كان ناجحاً جداً بحيث أنه يبني حالياً
a new hospital every 35 days.
مستشفى جديد كل 35 يوماً.
And 1298 Ambulances decided that it was going to
و 1298 سيارة إسعاف قرروا أنهم سيقومون
reinvent a completely broken industry,
بإعادة إبتكار القطاع المحطم تماماً،
building an ambulance service in Bombay
ببناء خدمات إسعاف في بومباي
that would use the technology of Google Earth,
التي ستستخدم تكنلوجيا خرائط غوغل (Google Earth)،
a sliding scale pricing system
نظام أسعار بمستويات متدرجة
so that all people could have access,
بحيث يستطيع كل الناس الحصول على الخدمات،
and a severe and public decision
وخدمة وقرار عام
not to engage in any form of corruption.
بعدم الضلوع في أي نوع من الفساد.
So that in the terrorist attacks of November
بحيث أنهم خلال الهجوم الإرهابي في نوفمبر
they were the first responder,
كانوا ضمن أوائل المستجيبين،
and are now beginning to scale, because of partnership.
وقد بدأوا الآن في التوسع، بسبب الشراكة.
They've just won four government contracts to build off their 100 ambulances,
لقد فازوا للتو بعقودات حكومية لتأسيس 100 إسعاف،
and are one of the largest and most effective ambulance companies
وهي أحد أكبر وأكثر شركات الإسعاف كفاءة
in India.
في الهند.
This idea of scale is critical.
فكرة الحجم مهمة للغاية.
Because we're starting to see these enterprises
لأننا بدأنا في رؤية هذه الشركات
reach hundreds of thousands of people. All of the ones I discussed
تصل مئات الملايين من الناس. وكل التي ناقشتها
have reached at least a quarter million people.
قد وصلت على الأقل لربع مليون شخص.
But that's obviously not enough.
لكن من الواضح أن ذلك غير كافي.
And it's where the idea of partnership
وهو حيث تصبح فكرة الشراكة
becomes so important.
مهمة للغاية.
Whether it's by finding those innovations
سواء كانت بإيجاد تلك الإبتكارات
that can access the capital markets,
التي يمكن أن تحصل على أسواق رأس المال،
government itself, or partner with major corporations,
الحكومة نفسها، أو الشراكة مع مؤسسات كبيرة،
there is unbelievable opportunity for innovation.
هناك فرصة مذهلة للإبتكار.
President Obama understands that.
الرئيس أوباما يفهم ذلك.
He recently authorized the creation of a Social Innovation Fund
لقد سمح مؤخراً بإنشاء صندوق إبتكار إجتماعي
to focus on what works in this country,
للتركيز على ما ينفع في هذه البلاد،
and look at how we can scale it.
والنظر لكيفية توسعتها.
And I would submit that it's time to consider
وأريد أن أعلن بأنه الوقت لنضع في الإعتبار
a global innovation fund
صندوق إبتكار عالمي
that would find these entrepreneurs around the world
الذي سيجد رجال الأعمال هؤلاء حول العالم
who really have innovations, not only for their country,
الذين لديهم حقاً إبتكارات، ليس فقط لبلدانهم،
but ones that we can use in the developed world as well.
لكن إبتكارات يمكن إستخدامها في الدول المتقدمة أيضاً.
Invest financial assistance, but also management assistance.
إستثمر في المساعدات المالية، لكن أيضاً في المساعدات الإدارية.
And then measure the returns,
ثم قم بتقييم العائدات،
both from a financial perspective
من وجهة النظر المالية،
and from a social impact perspective.
ومن وجهة نظر التأثير الإجتماعي.
When we think about new approaches to aid,
حينما نفكر بالمقاربات الحديثة للمساعدات،
it's impossible not to talk about Pakistan.
فمن المستحيل عدم الحديث عن باكستان.
We've had a rocky relationship with that country
كانت لدينا علاقات قوية مع تلك الدولة
and, in all fairness,
وبكل إنصاف
the United States has not always been a very reliable partner.
لم تكن الولايات المتحدة دائماً شريكاً يُعتمد عليه.
But again I would say that this is our moment
لكن مجدداً سأقول أنها فرصتنا
for extraordinary things to happen.
لنفعل أشياء غير إعتيادية.
And if we take that notion of a global innovation fund,
وإذا أخذنا مفهوم صندوق الإبتكار العالمي،
we could use this time to invest
يمكننا إستخدام هذا الوقت للإستثمار
not directly in government, though we would have government's blessing,
ليس مباشرة في الحكومة، رغماً عن أننا سنحصل على مباركة الحكومة،
nor in international experts,
وليس في الخبراء الدوليين،
but in the many existing entrepreneurs
لكن في العديد من رجال الأعمال الموجودين
and civil society leaders
وقادة المجتمع المدني
who already are building wonderful innovations
الذين يبنون بالفعل إبتكارات مدهشة
that are reaching people all across the country.
التي تصل إلى الناس عبر البلاد.
People like Rashani Zafar,
أناس مثل راشاني ظفار.
who created one of the largest microfinance banks in the country,
التي أسست أحد أكبر بنوك التمويل الجزئي في البلاد،
and is a real role model for women inside and outside the country.
وقدوة حقيقية للنساء داخل وخارج البلاد.
And Tasneem Siddiqui, who developed a way
وتسنيم صديقي الذي طوّر طريقة
called incremental housing,
تسمى الإسكان الإضافي،
where he has moved 40,000 slum dwellers
حيث قام بنقل 40 ألف من سكان الاحياء الفقيرة
into safe, affordable community housing.
إلى إسكان مجتمعي آمن وبأسعار معقولة.
Educational initiatives like DIL and The Citizen Foundation
المبادرات التعليمية مثل DIL ومؤسسة المواطن
that are building schools across the country.
التي تبني المدارس عبر البلاد.
It's not hyperbole
إنها ليست مبالغة
to say that these civil society institutions
للقول بأن تلك المؤسسات الإجتماعية المدنية
and these social entrepreneurs
ورجال الأعمال الإجتماعيون هؤلاء
are building real alternatives to the Taliban.
يقومون ببناء بدائل حقيقية لطالبان.
I've invested in Pakistan for over seven years now,
لقد إستثمرت في باكستان لأكثر من سبع سنوات الآن
and those of you who've also worked there
وأؤلئك منكم الذين عملوا هناك أيضاً
can attest that Pakistanis are an incredibly hard working population,
يمكن أن يشهدوا بأن الباكستانيين شعب يعمل بجدية لا تصدق.
and there is a fierce upward mobility in their very nature.
وهناك حراك إجتماعي لأعلى في طبيعتهم العادية.
President Kennedy said that
الرئيس كينيدي قال أن
those who make peaceful revolution impossible
أؤلئك الذين يجعلون الثورة السلمية مستحيلة
make violent revolution inevitable.
يجعلون ثورة العنف حتمية.
I would say that the converse is true.
وأود القول أن العكس هو الصحيح.
That these social leaders
بأن قادة المجتمع أؤلئك
who really are looking at innovation
الذين يتطلعون فعلاً للإبتكار
and extending opportunity
ويوسعون الفرصة
to the 70 percent of Pakistanis who make less than two dollars a day,
ل 70 بالمائة من الباكستانيين الذي يجنون أقل من دولارين يومياً،
provide real pathways to hope.
يقدمون طريقاً حقيقياً نحو الأمل.
And as we think about how we construct aid for Pakistan,
وبينما نفكر حول كيفية تقديم مساعدات لباكستان،
while we need to strengthen the judiciary,
بينما نحتاج لتعزيز السلطة القضائية،
build greater stability,
ونبني إستقراراً أكبر،
we also need to think about lifting those leaders
نحتاج أيضاً للتفكير برفع أؤلئك القادة
who can be role models for the rest of the world.
الذين بمستطاعهم لعب دور القدوة لبقية العالم.
On one of my last visits to Pakistan,
في زيارتي الأخيرة لباكستان
I asked Dr. Sono if he would take me
طلبت من الدكتور سونو إن كان ليأخذني
to see some of the drip irrigation in the Thar Desert.
لرؤية الري بالتنقيط في صحراء ثار.
And we left Karachi one morning before dawn.
وقد غادرنا كراتشي صباح أحد الأيام قبل الفجر.
It was about 115 degrees.
وقد كانت حوالي 115 درجة.
And we drove for eight hours
وقدنا لحوالي ثماني ساعات
along this moonscape-like landscape
عبر هذا المشهد كسطح القمر
with very little color, lots of heat,
مع لون طفيف، الكثير من السخونة،
very little discussion, because we were exhausted.
القليل من النقاش، لأننا كنا متعبين.
And finally, at the end of the journey,
وأخيراً في نهاية الرحلة
I could see this thin little yellow line across the horizon.
أستطعت رؤية خط رفيع أصفر عبر الأفق.
And as we got closer, its significance became apparent.
وكلما أقتربنا يصبح تفرده أكثر وضوحاً.
That there in the desert
هناك في الصحراء
was a field of sunflowers growing seven feet tall.
كان حقل زهرة الشمس ينمو بارتفاع سبعة أقدام.
Because one of the poorest farmers on Earth
لأن أحد أفقر المزارعين على الأرض
had gotten access to a technology
حصل على التكنلوجيا
that had allowed him to change his own life.
التي سمحت له بتغيير حياته.
His name was Raja,
كان أسمه راجا.
and he had kind, twinkly hazel eyes
ولديه عيون لامعة عسلية،
and warm expressive hands
وأيدي دافئة معبّرة
that reminded me of my father.
التي ذكرتني بوالدي.
And he said it was the first dry season
وقد قال أنه كان أول موسم جاف
in his entire life that he hadn't taken
طوال حياته بحيث أنه أخذ
his 12 children and 50 grandchildren
أولاده ال 12 وأحفاده ال 50
on a two day journey across the desert
في رحلة يومين عبر الصحراء
to work as day laborers at a commercial farm
للعمل باليومية في مزرعة تجارية
for about 50 cents a day.
لحوالي 50 سنتاً لليوم.
Because he was building these crops.
لأنه كان يقيم هذه المحاصيل.
And with the money he earned he could stay this year.
وبالمال الذي كسبه أستطاع البقاء هذه السنة.
And for the first time ever in three generations,
ولأول مرة على الإطلاق لثلاثة أجيال،
his children would go to school.
سيذهب أولاده إلى المدرسة.
We asked him if he would send his daughters as well as his sons.
سألناه إن كان سيرسل بناته أيضاً كما سيرسل أولاده.
And he said, "Of course I will.
وقد قال، "بالتأكيد سأفعل.
Because I don't want them discriminated against anymore."
لأنني لا أريدهم أن يفرقوا بينهم بعد الآن."
When we think about solutions to poverty,
حينما نفكر بالحلول لمشكلة الفقر
we cannot deny individuals
لا يمكننا إستبعاد الأفراد
their fundamental dignity.
وأساس كرامتهم.
Because at the end of the day,
لأنه في نهاية اليوم
dignity is more important to the human spirit than wealth.
الكرامة أكثر أهمية للنفس البشرية من الثروة.
And what's exciting is to see so many entrepreneurs across sectors
وما يثيريني هو رؤية العديد من رجال الأعمال عبر القطاعات
who are building innovations that recognize
الذين يقيمون إبتكارات تعترف
that what people want is freedom
بأن ما يحتاجه الناس هو الحرية
and choice and opportunity.
والإختيار والفرصة.
Because that is where dignity really starts.
لأن الكرامة تبدأ فعلاً من هناك.
Martin Luther King said that
قال مارتن لوثر كينغ أن
love without power is anemic and sentimental,
الحب بلا قوة مصاب بفقر الدم والعواطف.
and that power without love
والقوة بدون حب
is reckless and abusive.
هي طيش وتعسف.
Our generation has seen both approaches tried,
إن جيلنا شهد محاولة كلا المقاربتين،
and often fail.
وفشل دائماً .
But I think our generation also might be the first
لكني أعتقد أن جيلنا أيضاً ربما يكون الأول
to have the courage to embrace both love and power.
الذي يحصل على الشجاعة لإحتضان كلا الحب والقوة.
For that is what we'll need, as we move forward
لهذا فان ما نحتاجه بينما نمضي قدماً
to dream and imagine what it will really take
هو أن نحلم وأن نتخيل ما يتطلبه فعلاً
to build a global economy that includes all of us,
لبناء إقتصاد عالمي يشملنا جميعاً.
and to finally extend that fundamental proposition
وأخيراً لتوسيع تلك المسألة
that all men are created equal to every human being on the planet.
بأن جميع البشر وُلدوا متساوين، لكل شخص على كوكب الأرض.
The time for us to begin innovating
إنه وقتنا لبداية الإبتكار
and looking for new solutions, a cross sector, is now.
والنظر لحلول جديدة، عبر القطاعات هو الآن.
I can only talk from my own experience,
يمكنني فقط الحديث من تجربتي الخاصة.
but in eight years of running Acumen fund,
لكن بعد ثماني سنوات من إدارة صندوق أكيومن،
I've seen the power of patient capital.
لقد رأيت قوة رأس المال الصبور.
Not only to inspire innovation and risk taking,
ليس فقط لإلهام الإبتكار وأخذ المخاطر،
but to truly build systems that have created
لكن لبناء أنظمة حقيقية قامت بخلق
more than 25,000 jobs
أكثر من 25 ألف وظيفة
and delivered tens of millions of services and products
وقدمت مئات الملايين من الخدمات والمنتجات
to some of the poorest people on the planet.
لبعض أفقر الناس على كوكب الأرض.
I know it works.
أنا أعرف أنها ستنجح.
But I know that many other kinds of innovation also work.
لكني أعرف الكثير من الأنواع الأخرى للإبتكار ستنجح أيضاً.
And so I urge you, in whatever sector you work,
ولذا، أحثكم، في أي قطاع تعملون فيه،
in whatever job you do,
في أي وظيفة تعملون ،
to start thinking about how we might
لتبدأوا بالتفكير حول كيف قد يكون
build solutions that start
بناء الأنظمة التي ستبدأ
from the perspective of those we're trying to help.
من وجهة نظر أؤلئك الذين يحاولون المساعدة.
Rather than what we think that they might need.
بدلاً عن ما نعتقد أنه سيساعدهم.
It will take embracing the world with both arms.
سأقوم باحتضان العالم بكلا يدي.
And it will take living with the spirit of generosity and accountability,
وسأعيش على روح الكرم والمساءلة،
with a sense of integrity and perseverance.
مع شعور بالمثابرة والنزاهة.
And yet these are the very qualities
وهذه هي الصفات
for which men and women have been honored
التي كرّمت الرجال والنساء
throughout the generations.
عبر الأجيال.
And there is so much good that we can do.
وهناك الكثير من الخير الذي نستطيع فعله.
Just think of all those sunflowers in the desert.
فقط فكروا بأزهار عباد الشمس تلك في الصحراء.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)